<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A prospective for King and subjects. Or A schort discovery of some treacheries acted against Charles the I. and Charles the II. Kings of England, Scotland, and Ireland. With some few advertisements to the people in the 3. nations concerning the cruel, exorbitant, and most tyrannical slavery they are now under which they have wrought themselves into, and stil desiring to be, by up-holding of a pretended court of Parliament, altogether ruling contrary to the lawes of the lands or any branch there of and according to there owne lustful and arbitrary wills. Written by Wendy Oxford once an honourer of them and there pretences, but now as great an abhorrer of there Macheeslian practises.</title>
            <author>Oxford, Wendy.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53762</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214667</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826762</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826762</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31168</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53762)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31168)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1769:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A prospective for King and subjects. Or A schort discovery of some treacheries acted against Charles the I. and Charles the II. Kings of England, Scotland, and Ireland. With some few advertisements to the people in the 3. nations concerning the cruel, exorbitant, and most tyrannical slavery they are now under which they have wrought themselves into, and stil desiring to be, by up-holding of a pretended court of Parliament, altogether ruling contrary to the lawes of the lands or any branch there of and according to there owne lustful and arbitrary wills. Written by Wendy Oxford once an honourer of them and there pretences, but now as great an abhorrer of there Macheeslian practises.</title>
                  <author>Oxford, Wendy.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by John Pricton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed to [sic] Leyden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeare 1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31168:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31168:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A proſpective for King and ſubjects.</p>
            <p>OR A ſchort diſcovery of ſome treacheries acted againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the I. and <hi>Charles</hi> the II. <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With</hi> Some few advertiſements to the people in the 3. Nations concerning the cruel, exorbitant, and moſt Tyrannical ſlavery they are now under which they have wrought themſelves into, and ſtil deſiring to be, by up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of a pretended court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> altogether ruling contrary to the Lawes of the Lands or any branch there of, and according to there owne Luſtful and arbitrary wills.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Romanes the <hi>11.</hi> chap: verſe the <hi>4.</hi>
               </bibl> But I haue reſerved <hi>7000.</hi> man who have not bowed there Knees to Baal.</q>
            <p>Written by <hi>Wendy Oxford</hi> once an honourer of them and there pretences, but now as great an abhorrer of there Macheeſlian practiſes.</p>
            <q>Let St. Pauls Epiſtle to the Romanes, be now judge againſt ſuch Antichriſtian Romancing Rulers, as are aſſembled together at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Romanes 1. Chapt. and the 24. and 25. verſes.</hi>
               </bibl> Wherefore God gave them up to uncleaſſeneſſe, and to the change the truth into alie, worshipping the creature more then the creatour.</q>
            <p>Printed to Leyden by Iohn Pricton in the Ieare 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:31168:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31168:2"/>
            <head>To the Moſt High and Mighty ſufferer of this age Charles the II. by the grace of God, Right and true Borne King of England, Scotland, and Ireland.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Gracious Souveraigne.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEfore I begge your ſacred Majeſtyes patroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing this mite, which shal be conneighed into your natur all ſoyles, for as wel correction to your enemies, as alſo the cherishing of the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinge and dying people therein, who have layd long greived and languiſhing under an arbitrary power. I beſeech you to remember the advice given to your royal Father of bleſſed memory by a wiſe man. Make not knowne the cheifeſt of your determinations to an open councell (al thoughſtyled a privy councel) leaſt you faile in the diſigne, <hi>vera, amicitia, tantum modo eſt inter bonos mali nec interſe amici ſunt, nec cum bonis,</hi> Neither doe any thing of great concernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in councel of a civil freind, in vvhich your Majeſty cannot be ſafe in the execution thereof unleſſe it be concealed: <hi>Civilem amicum ſic habeas ut putes poſſe in imicúm fieri. Admire</hi> not (Gracious Sr.) that in a corner of the earth I vvhiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per this councel unto you, for had your ſacred Father beleived the ſame he had never beene ſo unhappy as to be murthered by his ovvne people (nay by ſom of thoſe he made his boſome freinds) and conſequently your royal ſelfe had not beene expoſed to ſuch termes as your ovvne ſoule, better knovves then any. <hi>But
<pb facs="tcp:31168:3"/>vincit qui patitur.</hi> No I vvrit this ſmal enſueing trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe unto your Majeſty that you may have an inſight of vvhat you haue done, and the better you vval diſcerne vvhat is to be done, by remooving al ſychophauts vvho lay parſonally in the breaſt of your Fathers and your Majeſtyes, but there harts in the treaſury of both your knovvne enemies. <hi>Latet anguis in herba!</hi> and ſtil the ſeeds of thoſe adamites are ingendring in your councels which (gracious Prince) I hold my ſelfe bound induty to make knowne to your Majeſty, &amp; thereby give a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat to you for the future, ſeing the glory of God &amp; the good of my Soveraigne, and 3 commonwalths at ſtake If your Majeſty ſhould diſcountenance the worke, my comfort remaines that the frowe of my Prince may turne to the favour of my God <hi>nec mendacii utilitas eſt diuturna, nec veritatis damnum diu nocet,</hi> neither ſhal flattery ſtil hold in credit, nor truth alway continue in diſgrace. No no (Great Sr.) none but ſuch as joyne with your Enemies (knowing you to be Heire apparent of ſo great a monarch (who was not only defender of the faith, but martyre thereof) dares be tacite (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) when the chriſtian fayth lyes wallowing in the blood of its owne ſaints over the whole earth in your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteys being ſo unlawfully kept from that Scepter, which uſvally did protect the innocent, and detect the nocent: which that it may once more be put in the hand of your righteous ſelfe the vicegerent of the Lords, I here on my bended knees offer unto the moſt high my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt praiers for your Majeſtyes ſafety, and in throning (not doubting but your gracious goodneſſe will grant protection to theſe my deſires) and that as dayes
<pb facs="tcp:31168:3"/>multiplies on your haires and yeares on your people, that the weiſdome of God and ſavour of your owne ſubjects may be joyned with the helpe of al chriſtian princes (making it there owne caſes) to the reſtablishing of your Majeſtyes 3. Crownes. This ſuit wil I never give ouer, in al others, I wil remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſtyes faythful and obedient ſubject during lyfe.</hi> Wendy Oxford.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:31168:4"/>
            <head>The Epistle to every free borne ſubject of England, Scotland, and Ireland.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Countryman.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Deſire not to hold thee long in the porche, but intreat thee to enter into the houſe, where if thou findeſt any thing which thou canſt cal thine, I pray take it, and of the reſt, if there be any thing which may doe thee good in the time of peace or warre, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation or proſperity, accept thereof, but as thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt it, I begge of thee to obſerve wel, and be an impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall judge of the truth thereof, which if thou beeſt there in reſolved, doe not only of (what is true) lay up, where theeves may breake through and ſteale it away, but lay the good ſo up, that thou Majeſt (upon a good op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity) make good uſe thereof to the freeing thy ſelfe from the thraldome thou art under, and the dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kneſſe of thy Salvation thou art kept in by thoſe who made the glory of God, and thy freedome from Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, there pretences, &amp; ſtalking horſes, but they rule notouer you as chriſtians or as the beloved of the Lord but as Servants forcing you to make bricke without ſtraw. Which that you may be freed from, by a moſt Faythfull Moſes, ſhalbe the harty praiers and wel wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shis of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy loving countryman and Brother in Chriſt.</hi> Wendy Oxford.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:31168:4"/>
            <head>A Proſpective for KING AND SVBIECTS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have read of William Rufus a King of England was ſlaine with an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Shotte at a hart by a knight, and in an other Hiſtory I find that <hi>Baſilius Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedo A Romaine Emperour</hi> was killed with the ſtroake of a hart in hunting, <hi>Cajus</hi> and <hi>Fulvius Valerius Anaſtaſius</hi> (wee read alſo) the Emperours periſhed by lightning, as alſo young <hi>Druſus Pompey</hi> the Sonne of the Emperour <hi>Claudius</hi> was choa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with a peare which he caſt up and caught it in his mouth in a ſportiue way, ſo likewiſe of <hi>Charles</hi> King of Navarre wee read he came to a ſtrange and untimely death, for he being ſewed up in a ſheet by night that he might be bathed in it, he that ſeued it, went to burne of the thread with the cand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, and ſet fire on the ſheet, ſo that the King being ſo much ſcorched with the heat, died threon in three dayes. You may likewiſe read of <hi>Euripiudes</hi> of very great fame who was unawares torne to peeces by doggs and (as plyny writeth) An acreon was choaked with the ſtone of a Rayſin, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius with a haire in a meſſe of milke, yea I read of Plinie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfs periſhed by a ſtronge fire of mount Veveſus Whilſt he was ſeeking to know the reaſon thereof, ſome ends there lives in laughing as Valerius Maximus, others by ſneezing, and as I began with a King of England I wil end with a King of England, whom weread was buggered with a hot ſpitt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31168:5"/>through a horne into his fundament up into his body, but this was a cruel act of privacy, but never did you read or heare of any Prince or King murthered after ſuch a manner as <hi>Charles</hi> the I. was on the 30. day of Ianu. 1648. about 2. of the clocke in the afternoone, niether did I ever heare or read of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Kings or princes ſo much laid ſnares for &amp; ſo much betrayd as there have beene together, vide: <hi>King Iames, King Charles</hi> the I. and <hi>King Charles</hi> the II. And if you wil force me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive there hath, I muſt confeſſe there hath beene trache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which haue beene acted againſt Kings, and Princes, but ſtil have beene diſcovered, before execution, as Caeſar whoſe life was taken from him as he was goeing to the ſenate houſe; yet it was diſcovered to him in a letter before, if he had read it, to have beleeved it; ſo, many plotts there was againſt the late Queene Eliſabeth, ſome dangerous ons againſt King Iames, but put them altogether, they reach not at the throngs of treacheries, in this our age. For the cheifeſt of your Royal Fathers Nobility, (Dread Soveraigne) and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, nay whom he made Noble, and whom he preſerved from periſhing, nay let mee goe higher; ſome, whom he (by his gracious goodneſſe) redeemed from death, which they were condemned unto by Iuſtice for treaſon againſt him ſelfe, and others formurther; Theſe very people being choſen councellours to him, not only betrayed him from there very beginning of there truſts repoſed in them, as to the looſing his peoples harts, but alſo in the renting his Kingdomes, and al the territories thereunto belonging from him and his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, nay not reſting there, but in the concluſion (caſting of the name of treachery) they preſumed to take away his life, under the colour of Iuſtice by a Pylate and phariſaical judges openly to condemne him in the ſame Hal, whre they ſhould juſtly haue died formerly, and then executed there cruel murther on him at the gates of his owne court, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſcaffold openly in the face of his owne people, as if he had
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:31168:5"/>beene a traitor to himſelfe, nay they cutt his ſacred life of in the moſt ignominous way that could be inmagined, even as the greateſt traitor that ever was ſince England received chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrianty even by the hand of the common Hangman belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Tyburne. O prodigious Monſters? whoſe perſons and actions ſhalbe ſome what laid forth in this booke, when I come to my adviſe to the poore blinded people: but they are more at large painted out to the life in my booke intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. The baniſ hed mans complaint comming forth.</p>
            <p>Should I begin at the ſuſt of King Iames, and ſo deſcend to this very day of al the treacheries which have beene acted at home in councels, and a broad againſt the States of the 3. Kingdomes, I ſhould be in a laborinth, and weary the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders patience, wherefore I wil but cull out ſome remarkable ons, and indeed but poynt at ſome of them, enough for for your gracious Majeſty to perſeive what is meant in the whole.</p>
            <p>Did not your royal Father of Bleſſed memory (al though ſo cruſified by his owne ſubjects) put his whole truſt of the managing, the whole affaires of his Kingdomes in to the hands of his councel: and was he not betrayed (before ever a Parliament was called) by ſome of them, ſworne privy councellers, was it not plainely ſeene that there was a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh purſe alwaies open a mongſt them, was not the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh faction moulded ſo high with the riches of the Indies, that never ſince Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> died, revenge could be endeavoured againſt the inſolent but ſubtile Spaniard. And was not there a French pox in other ſome of his councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours cauſing a rottenneſſe in there harts, to the Keeping his then Maieſty from maiking warres &amp; regaining the loſt clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of that Crowne, and when at laſt, ſome more honeſt then the reſt did perſwade an army to beſent over, did not then golden french Piſtols (by treacheary) overcome the Engliſh Steele, whoſe edge formerly was a terrour to al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31168:6"/>And with leave (Great Prince) was not your royal Father betrayed in al his privy councels, councels of warre, and in his very bedchamber at Yorke, Shrewsbury and Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, was there ever any thing of conſiquence, acted there in, nay but ſpoke on, or was ever deſigne but intended on his Enemies in the field, or upon any Garriſon, but it was preſently ſent away to the General, or Scontmaſter General of his Enimies, or to the Commander in cheife, of the next Gariſon of Enemies, or if time would premit to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitty of ſafety, then ſitting at Darby Houſe, was it not that your Fathers Enimies there treaſury was greater then his (they having the revenues of al his, the Royal Queenes, &amp; your then Princely ſelfe with your Brothers the Duke of Yorke, and moſt of al the nobility and greateſt gentery in the whole Kingdome, beſides there dayly aſſeſments and loanes, and ſubſidies with many other extraordinary taxes, as exciſes of al things, together with the infinite and vaſt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of monyes raiſed on Biſhops, Deanes and chapters lauds, enough to purhaſe whole Armyes, Townes, and Cities, as in concluſion they did, for were not thereby whole Armyes, Cities, Gariſons of Townes, and Forts ſold to his then Maieſtyes, and now continuing yours; are not the prover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes too too much veryfied in theſe latterdayes. Monyes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes the mare to goe: and an aſſe laden with gold ſhal enter in to the ſtrongeſt city or towne what ever, and the golden Key unlocke the ſtrongeſt gates that are, yes, your Maiſty ſees and feeles the truth hereof. For no ſooner was the ſacred life of your deare Father and our ſoveraigne taken away, but immediatly meſſages weere ſent to ſome about your ſacred ſelfe for the holding of correſpondency with them at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter which the very buſineſſe of Bredah ſpeakes ſomething thereof, for no ſooner was anything done (altough never ſo privatly thought) but with in 3. dayes the whole reſult was at Whitehal (that once a royal ſeat for our Kings and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31168:6"/>Queenes but now a denne of thieves) which would have beene made good to your Maieſty by ſome what wiſhed hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to you at the hague, but truth was cruſſhed in the ſhel, and thoſe blaſted for there good intentions: But pardon mee (Gracious Sr.) that I am ſo plaine, I moſt humbly beſeech your gracious Majeſty. I muſt now goe a long with your Maieſtyes councellours from Bredah into Schotland, from whence I muſt tel your gracious goodneſſe there was dayly poſtings betweene ſome of your chrifeſt pretended friends and your openeſt Enemies, (O Sr.) there have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded a world of teacheries, as firſt concerning the holding your Maieſty from taking the Covenant until your thro at was ready to be, cut the ſteele of your Enimies being thereby prepared, thoſe treacherous vermins that put triphles into your conceience were hired thereunto, for that your Enimies knew, the ſchotts nation would not truſt you nor fight for you, until you had done it, and alſo theſcotts, Iuncto would not doe there ut moſt in raiſing of an Army until they had your conſcience engaged, which was too late, when you had taken it, for by that time, your Enimies became maſters of the field. Next looke upon that moſt traiterous act of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering up of Edenburgh, Caſtle and Leith, was not 20000. paid downe for it and the Governour thereof now the only man with your Enemies, then was it not a ſylver bridge that conveyed your Enemies over in to Fife, did not the ſilver ore quench the heat of Brent I laud, and ſo al along in your Maieſtyes whole progreſſe in Scotland, to be ſhort hath not monyes conquered al Scotland.</p>
            <p>Now (moſt ſuffering Prince) give mee leave to march a long with your councellours from ſterling into England, where they layd the plott your Maieſtye ſhould be katched in a trappe, to that end you were ſuſſered to goe without let or moleſtation, your Enemies being aſſured before hand, that you ſhould not march to London, where you had fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31168:7"/>your deſines. What was it but monyes that hindered you from ſuffering the gallant Cavalery under the Duke of Bucks, earle of Cleveland, and Maſſy, to fal on your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies at Torwood where God had deſigned there for your prey had you not beene betrayed. What was it but monyes that when your Maieſty was adviſed by ſome of your muſt faithful ſubjects to march immediatly to London, that you were adviſed too lay downe before Carlile a daye &amp; night, on ſet purpoſe that Lambert and Harriſon Major Generals of 2. brigades of your enemies, horſe might be joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and that Cromwel General of your enemies might come up in the reare of your army who was at leaſt 9. dayes march from you, yes, it was monyes that did al this, and thoſe very perſons that received it now lye in priſon for a colour, but ſpend after that extraordinary manner, as if they were more then free ſubjects. Againe was it not 30000. paid to ſome appoynted to receive it, that cauſed David Leſly (when as your Majeſty had given the Duke of Bucks and that gallant gentleman Maſſy 500. horſe to goe a part from your army, and when the Duke ſent for 500. horſe more with the harty deſire of doeing ſome acceptable peece of ſervice in breaking an aſſociated committee of Traitors met from divers counties for the raiſing forces againſt your Majeſty, which the ſaid Duke might eaſily have taken and diſperſed them every on had his grace had the 500. horſe ſent for) what was it cauſed David Leſly to come unto your Majeſty and tel you that the Duke was a young ſouldier, and would engage your whole army, and ſo cauſe a loſſe of al preſently (which he by a lingring way loſt in the end) which cauſed your Majeſty immediatly to ſend an expreſſe order under your owne hand &amp; ſeale for the calling backe the Dake of Bucks to your body: and what was it but a Sylver barre that croſſed your rode to London, and what was it that when your army had the bal at there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eet at waring
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31168:7"/>ton Bridge and your enemies Lambert and Harniſon at the mercy of your army, that they were ſuffered to goe a way untouched, nay ſuffering many faithful and gallant gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen (who were on the for lorne hope) to be taken and caryed away priſoners within leſſe then muſket ſhort of your whole army, and but by a ſmal party of the enemy, yet not releaſed by your Generals command but contrary command given that none ſhould ſtirre. Next let mee remind your faced ſelfe of the many treachirous acts at Worceſter, as firſt the advice of being drawne to that place of no ſtrength, to be taken in a nett as a covey of partridges: Secondly when as halfe of the army of your enemies were marched under the command of L. General Fleet wood by up ton over the bridge and ſo came cloſe to the other ſide Worceſter, which is in compaſſe 18. Miles diſtant on part from the other part of your enemies army, I ſay what was it that kept your Majeſty from ſighting on or the other part of your enemies when your Majeſty was adviſed to it in the ſteeple of Worceſter minſter, againe what was it that cauſed your Majeſty to ſuſſer a bridge of boates to be made within muſket ſhott of the towne of Worceſter, for your enemies to releive on another as they ſhould ſee occaſion, and the enemy to make it without diſturbance; Laſtly (as to Worceſter treachery) what was the cauſe that when ſome came and told your Majeſty (as you were at dinner) that the enemy was comeing on, and ſome perſons of Honour deſired that they might goe out with a party and charge that bold enemy which was comeing on, but David Leſly gave order to the contrary (ſaying) let them come on I-ſe make them to garre faether in one houre, then they ſhal come on in three, which neglect and treachery in concluſion proved to the utter overthrow of your Majeſty, the great loſſe of your nobility &amp; gentry, and as much as in him lay the loſſe of 3. Kingdomes, O Sir, it was not for want of courage
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31168:8"/>or diſcipline, but your enemies purſe that ſealed un aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of victory to your enemies, it was that formerly which gave victory of above 28000. gallant men under Duke Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons command in 1648. to 8000. under Cromwels conduct in Lancaſhire: for the nations know, there was not a blow ſtrucke to any commander for the victory but to the Duke in Weſtminſter halyard. So that your Majeſly plainly ſees your ſelfe bereaved of duty ſidelity and valour of al ſides, as your ſubjects beguiled of there allegiance, by being ſeduced with faire pretences on the on ſide, and your ſubjects in ſnared to ſlaufhter on the other by treacherous vermins, O have not many armies in your royal fathers time beene ſtrong in bulke, but weakned by factions amongſt the cheife, which cauſed his commanders (not conſiding in on another) to provide for there owne ſafety and ſubſiſtence, what was it that bred theſe diſtempers but the Parliaments coyne, which the plaine country man ſaw likewiſe and made him draw his necke out of the choller. My duty (dread Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) teaches mee to let you know as much of the treacheries and corruptions of your enemies as I wel know, which in breife, is, that which you cannot be ignorant of that there is ſuch a large allowance of monyes to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of ſtate (ſtyled) for the rewarding of in formers, Spies, and intelligencers even to betray there neareſt freinds in all relations, ſo that where blood and the neareſt conſanguinity can not find ſecurity of councel and action, it is in veine for a Prince to hold himſelfe ſafe in many coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors: great emperours, Princes, and generals in theſe our dayes (who have made uſe of councellors as to heare the opinions of every on of them) but they had never effected ſuch great attempts as they did, had they not kept the reſult of al in there owne harts until the very houre which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the enterprize: may I be on ce bleſſed with the ſight of your Majeſty I ſhal be more plaine in my expreſſions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31168:8"/>then now I am, for that I oſſend ſome ſo much, that this poore booke could not find a preſſe until the ſoarings were a little clipped: and if by my expreſſions and confeſſions which I ſhal then lay open to your Majeſtyes judgement, Iſhal not irritate your diſpleaſure, but merit your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pardon, it wil engage mee too make the greater diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very es, which I ſhal for beare to any what ever but my owne Prince. But thus much I ſhal preſume on in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim, that your Majeſty be cautions of ſome neare you, and then feare not thoſe farre from you.</p>
            <p>And let this be a cave at to the Dutch, for no queſtion if it be poſſibly to corrupt any of there greateſt States, which God for bid thoſe of Weſtminſter wil not be wanting to the ut moſt of there endeavours and ſtocks (which En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland with greife may ſay) are to great. (great Prince) caſt of ſuch ſychophants (as I ſayd already) whoſe perſons are with your Majeſty, and there harts in the treaſury of your enemies, looke on thoſe (I bee ſeech your Majeſty on my knees) that have loſt there fathers, brothers, and kindred, nay al there eſtates for doeing you ſervice and your roy al father, I ſay caſt not not of your nobility and true harted gentry, they have ever beene formerly accounted ornaments to a crowne the on, and propps thereunto, the other, and al of moſt honourable reſpects in a republicke; Although I muſt confeſſe (in theſe our latter dayes) even as ſome deadly hem locke hath appeared in fertile ground, and the richeſt ore hath beene digged out of barren ſoyle, even ſo hath vertuons and honourable ſpirits proceeded from meane parentage, and appeared ſo in your ſervice, and baſe and ignoble, diſcended from Honourable progenitors, who have formerly appeared as ſtarres for there Princes, but now gone out as ſnuſſes of candles, againſt them; wherefore wel ſayd a holy man, nobility of birth maney times begets ignobility of mind, and untimely honour hinders many from honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31168:9"/>attempts but; to ſuch nobility, and ſuch councellours I conclude thus (which I deſire may be a caveat to the remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning honeſt of Lords and privy councellors) that great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe can not exempt them from the vengeance of God, nor al the wealth in the Parliaments treaſury bye them there from, which commandement (contrary to there knowledge and conſcience that they ſhould honour God and be true to ther King) they doe thus preſumptuouſly tranſgreſſe; which is neither Gods commandement cannot deterre, nor Gods Word adviſe them, nor his judgements feare them, I wil ſay as Saint John writes in the 12. Chap. of the revola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; the 11. verſe, he which is fylthy, let him by fylchy ſtill. Wherefore (moſt gracious Sr) I be ſeech you to leave ſuch councellours in time, leaſt your Majeſty be left by them in the lurch <hi>(A ſtander by many times ſees more then he that playeth)</hi> as your Majeſty hath beene too often already. Now (gracious King) be pleaſed too give a poore ſubject of your Majeſtyes leave to ſet downe a few advertiſements for the procuring your owne rights and Kingdoms. And firſt of al (Sr) I be ſeech your Majeſty as to deſcend ſo much, as to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe your ſelfe to your people in a he avenly way of peace, and goodneſſe by way of declerations, and remonſtrances, making there in a Covenant with God to follow your vowes and proteſtations made, or to be made to your ſubjects, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they have beene ſtubborne and ſtiſſe necked hitherto againſt you, yet behold and ſee what the Lord God of hoſts may doe with there harts: for (great Sr) thinke not to overcome them by ſword ſo eaſily as by word, no no, they have beene ſo long embrueng there hauds in bloods on af another, that there harts are hardned againſt forra igners you may bring in; they may be ſooner ſmitten with your aſſuance to them, that as you redeme your rights carefully, you wil not only ſpend them wiſely, but that you wil firſt of all ſettle the proteſtant religion amongſt them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31168:9"/>in the purity therof according to the beſt reformed churches, that when your Majeſtyes time ſhal come, when you muſt give an account to the King of Kings of your vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerency and Steward ſhip, the God of al Gods may ſay to you welcomely, Euge bone ſerve? and give your gracious ſelfe a Crowne of glory which ſhal never fal from the head of your Majeſty, and that your people may have juſt cauſe to mourne for ſuchan earthly loſſe, and rejoyce that you are els where in glory remaining for ever hereafter, which that your Majeſty may attaine unto here, and hereafter, God of his mercy graunt, Amen.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next that your Majeſty promiſe to rule over them with love, and not by feare, the loving way of government being eaſy and ſafe, but Tyranny is ever accompanied with care and terror (O Sr) carry this ſaying in your breaſt. <hi>Ama &amp; impera; Qui terret, plus ille timet, ſors illa Tyranno convenit.</hi> And truly (Deare Sr.) could your Majeſty be but quiet a while longer, your gracious ſelfe ſhould ſoone ſee this ſaying ſulfilled in the now oppreſſours of your people, there exorbitant oppreſſions wil force the oppreſſed to take an advantage of ſhaking of the yoke they are now under as not being able to beare any longer, neither wil Gods juſtice ſuffer the ſway which is grounded on there cruel Tyranny to continue.</p>
            <p>Now to theſe two principles which I begge your Majeſty to harken unto, let mee ſpeake to my country men concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them.</p>
            <p>Remember (fellow commoners) that you by Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and humane lawes, are the true and lawful ſubjects of this King who now you deraine his rights and your owne due obdience from. For heis your naturally borne King, and theſe you now yeild obedience unto in al there falſe edicts, have ſurruptiouſly gotten the ſtaſſe of government over you, and accordingly uſurpe there authority, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31168:10"/>they have gotten it by conqueſt, but alas they have not conquered there King, nor you, but it was you that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guered your ſelves, in conquering your Prince, and thoſe you fought againſt.</p>
            <p>Next remember good country men, and repent as you wil anſwer at the dreadfull day of judgement (when al your now uſurping rulers and your actions of treaſon and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers muſt be accounted for) of your holding downe your Prince by the haire of the head whilſt theſe bloodſucking rulers cut it of from his Sacred perſon remember when you did this murther, you wonded your God through the ſides, and ſo long as you fight againſt to keepe your native Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne from his rights and poſſeſſions, you deteyne God out of his right, the King being the vice gerent of the Lords ſo that in plaine termes you tobbe God of his dues and the King of his, contrary quite to our Savious rule give unto Caeſar the things which are Caeſars, and unto God thoſe things which are Gods.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Next (moſt renowned Prince) promiſe to the people that you wil doe juſtice to al (which is termed <hi>Regia men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura</hi>) even to the meaneſt as wel as to the greateſt without partiality, neither inclining to the right hand of affection nor to the left hand of hatred. I be ſeech you toread Sir <hi>Francis Bacons Eſſaies</hi> of Iudicature, wherein he ſpeaks to Prince as wel as to Iudges if thou per ceiveſt (ſayth he) on the on ſide high hils of advantage, powerful combination, and violent proſecution, and on the other ſide the low vallyes of poverty and dejected neſſe, prepoſe thy way as God did to judgement. <hi>Iſaiath the</hi> 40. <hi>Chap: and the</hi> 3. <hi>verſe,</hi> by raiſing vallies and taking downe mountaines, ſo ſhalt thou lay the foundation of thy ſentence on a ſure ground. Then O King as Iehoſaphat ſaid. Be of good courage, and doe juſtice, and the Lord wil be with thee and al nations ſhal feare thee.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:31168:10"/>
            <p>Now let me ſpeake againe to your people as to this 3. adviſe. And if ſo that ſuch promiſes be made to you (good countrymen) by a King, I and by your owne King, not a forreigner, by a proteſtant Prince of your owne religion, and not of aſtrangeon, that you ſhal have your religion reſetled, your lawes (now torne to peeces) reeſtabliſhed, ſo that in cauſes of juſtice and judgment you ſhal have true ſentence, <hi>Secundum allegata &amp; probata,</hi> and that you ſhal have Iudges like Elohem upon life and death, and like Solomon when meum &amp; tuum is in diſpute, and not like theſe Kingly uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, who (to your greifes I ſpeake it) had rather Ius dare, to make lawes of there owne upon there authorityes of <hi>ſic volumus, ſic Iubermus,</hi> not fearing at al that feareful malediction in Abekuke chapter the 5. and the 1. verſe. Curſed is he that remooveth his neighbours land marke, I ſay they had rather <hi>Ius dare,</hi> them <hi>Ius dicere</hi> then to pronounce the old lawes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made. If ſuch things be promiſed by our dread Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne; what ſhal let you (but an extraordinary judgement of God for your ſinne of in gratitude) from in throning him in his native rights, and yours, which wil prove in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion your freedomes, and greateſt gaines. But ſome of theſe mens, Baal preiſts may ſay what wil you extirpate thoſe you have choſen to make and preſerve your lawes? I anſwer, they deſerve it, having beene choſen by you to doe ſo, (nay they having ſworne ſo to doe,) but they have prooved falſe, for ſworne, and groſſe covenant breakers, who have wreſted the lawes of God, and the goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt to there owne ends: the Iuſtice of God requires it and man alſo, <hi>melius ut pereat unus, quam pereat unitas,</hi> better for on to periſh, then unity to be deſtroyed: they terme themſelves a Parliament, and as but on body, therefore let that on as a rotten corrupt, and putrified body be cut of to ſave a whole ſtocke from periſhing, <hi>Fiat Iuſtitia.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Enſe reſeindendum, ne pars ſincera trahatur,</q>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:31168:11"/>
            <p>Looke upon the Apoſtles rule. <hi>Nos ſcimus bonam eſſe legam, modò index à legitima utatur.</hi> We know that the law is good if a man uſe it lawfully.</p>
            <p>To the end of what hath beene hitherto ſpoken by mee I humbly begge of your Majeſty that I may returne unto you, and your goodneſſe heare mee.</p>
            <p>That your Majeſty would not be adviſed (by any favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites) when you ſhal (by Gods bleſſing) attaine to your crownes to deale with your people, as phyſitians ſometimes deale with there patients, that they muſt be recovered by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſives, and ſharpe remedies; no (Deare Sr.) that you pleaſe to cure them with a diat, and aſſwage with fomentations. And if againſt the light of nature, and lawes of nations and rights thereof, your people ſhal perſiſt in there obſtinacy, and contemne your many times offred grace, and goodneſſe, then you are excuſed, in the binding, cutting and pruning ſuch ſtife ſtakes (that wil rather burſt then bend) and al to be really looked on, as to the reſtoring your ſelfe to your owne, and them to your ſelfe, yet you may not extirpate all.</p>
            <p>But for the a voyding of this latter I wiſh (great Sr) that your Kingdomes may be ſetled without more blood, as firme as mountaines, not to be remooved, your cities returne in obedience, and your ſtrongholds with continuance of the ſame; al your ſubjects obſequious, and not to hate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy under thoughts of freedome, and ſo conſpire ſtil to with hold there obedience: O that is a greivous ſinne, and abſolutely unlawfull by the lawes of God and man, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve a redemption by a wicked temptation of liberty: Such ſubjects muſt expect to labour under general convulſions, and be waſted with unheard of Lacerations. No, farre be it from your people to entertaine ſuch precipitation of thoughts and farre be alſo contempt and rigour from your Majeſty, leaſt the divine power of God bring to paſſe that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31168:11"/>which few feares, none dare attempt, and Prince and people ab horre, wherefore (O Prince) reſolve of comeing to your owne (if poſſibly, by love and peace, and rather ſuffer a little longer then ruine al. <hi>Si vis vincere, diſce pati.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now you that cal your ſelves the ſupreame power of England Scotland and Ireland. I can compare you to no other then to the 30. Tyrants of Athens, or to the Tribunes amongſt the Romans, either lyke the 30. Tyrants who were choſen by the people to be there conſervators of there lawes and liberties, (even ſo were you) who held the people with goodwords and faire glozzed declarations (as you have done) until they had the opportunity, and ſtrength to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in there deſigne of Tyranny then they turned the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of the people againſt there owne breacts and became abſolute Tyrants whole names and deeds had never beene blotted out had not this age bred ſuch monſters as you are to outvy them in the highheſt manner that may be, or els you may be compared to the Tribunes amongſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, to be appealed unto from inferiour courts of Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature, and choſen Parliament men to be adviſers about affaires, and aſſiſtants to the King, which in a ſhort time, you by your machevilian perjuries, and ſo phiſticated con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurations to the people namely your declarations, promiſes, remonſtrances &amp;c. In your uſurped authority have not only overtopped the Kings power, like the Tribunes, but have cut of King, and power to al poſterity. Wherefore al people may juſtly ſay either you are without Chriſt, or Chriſt without peace, A hard ſaying (I muſt confeſſe) but yet more of truth then wonder which the church of God mourneth for ſuch diſcords, where in her beſt earthly Saints lye murthered by you, religion through out the world accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth your errors, and you who ſeeme to be profeſſours accuſe religion, by which meanes, Heretickes, Schiſmatickes,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31168:12"/>and Blaſphemors, Turkes, inſidels, and pagans, in ſult over Gods children and al of you over the church. But wherefore have you thus betrayed the honour of God, and battered his inheritance? O looke (ye vipers) what Kazienzen ſaith, <hi>ubi noſt eſt pax, non eſt Mundus:</hi> But I feare the ſaying of Iehu is upon you, what have you to doe with peace? The people have juſt cauſe to ſay of you, nay God himſelfe may ſay, you Hatter him with your praiers, and wound him with your ſwords; you have the voyce of Iacob, but the hands of Eſau, the viſage of innocent Abel, but the harts of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therous Cain; for you have made bonefires of whole townes in the 3. Kingdomes, and exhibited emblemes of your inflamed minds to the world, and al at the ſame time when you ſeeme to congratulate your thankefulneſſe to the Lord: but in theſe things you make God your ſtalking horſe, for whilſt you ſeeme to burne in cenſe, whole townes are turned in to ſmoake, O, your weapons reake not with the blood of Turkes, but in the hartbloods of your native King and fellow ſubjects. O what a miſerable reſolution have you cloathed your ſelves with, even to deſtroyall rather then be deſtroyed? Are you to be called miniſters of State, are you to be called peace makers, and phyſitians of a commonwealth, no, rather to be called firebrands of a Kingdome, or (in more law like termes) States barrators, who have blaſted the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of 3. Kingdomes by your litigious Iuglings, and you have deluded the people thereof into an univerſal ſorrow and complaint, groaning under the heavy preſſures of your taxations, being tilted (as empty barrels) in there fortunes by your avaritious and arbitrary exactions. And thoſe who have eſcaped your ſwords, you have bereaved of there eſtates, which muſt cauſe famine inevitably to depopulate by lingring deathes, others, who eſcaped, and yet under your power, live (as in apreſſe) under your tyrannous calamity: So that al, not only being ſequeſtred from light and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31168:12"/>of that which concernes there ſoules, but are alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred from there country habitations, that they are in a worſe condition then the ſoules of the ayre, neither having reſt nor food, &amp; you are not only ſufficed here with, but your thirſty blood ſucking ſoules (like the lapathae and Centau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res) who in warring ſeeke nothing but warre, ſuch are your haughty minds, that you thirſt after the blood of your nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring countryes of Scotland and Ireland, nay thoſe being dry land territories, can not quench your thirſts, wherefore you make warre on the ſeas, and with thoſe who were at peace with al the world, until ſuch time as your pride forceth them to adfence, and I doubt not but they (being borne under awatery climate) may ſatiate your bloody Stomackes and the Sulphering heat of your bound leſſe conſciences with water enough, which the Lord of hoſts grant they may cutt of as a curſe from the earth, and make good the ſaying of the Apoſtle. Cutt them downe, cut them downe, why cumber they the ground.</p>
            <p>Now according to my promiſe let mee whiſper a word or two to my blind, ignorant, and wilful countrymen, to ſuch as when there King having ſo often ventured his life for the ſaving theres, they like barbarians, and the worſt of heathens, requited good with evil.</p>
            <p>O countrymen remember Worceſter buſineſſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that from the firſt entrance of his Majeſty out of Scotland through great dangers and hardſhip by carlile and ſo a long to Worceſter that not 3. hundred of you came into the aſſiſtance (caſting of al duty and allegiance) to your Prince, but contrarily you ſtocked into the helpe of thoſe, that you cry dayly tyrannizeth over you, whoſe confuſions in your cuppes you drinke and the health and proſperity of your Prince, yet you are the firſt that would cutt his Majeſtyes throat, for did you not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it at Worceſter when you came to the aſſiſtance of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31168:13"/>Cromwel by Thouſands, and when that your King had loſt the day, you were worſe enemies to his nobility and gentry then any of Cromwels men, nay you hunted after the life of his then dis comfited Majeſty, like as the hunter doth after his prey: raping, and plundering al before you beating the braines out of the meaner ſort and hurrying the greater (after you had ſufficiently robbed them) to ſome traiterous committee or other for are ward. O Country-men, thinke you not that you muſt anſwer for theſe in humane, &amp; bloody acts, for theſe robberies, and murthers, you then &amp; formerly have committed contrary to the commandements of, thou ſhalt not ſteale, thou ſhallt doe no murther. Who is it for, that you have runne a hazard of damnation of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, and ſoules, it is even for thoſe, whoſe power can be no other (by the lawes of God and man) then a robbed uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping power, ſo that other nations have juſt cauſe now to ſay, <hi>Quales Magiſtri, tales ſervi.</hi> But he hold and read there peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preſented to his Majeſty (whom they wilfully mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered) on the 16. day of Iuly 1642. there you ſhal find that theſe uſurpers then called God of heaven and earth to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that they would defend his Majeſty from all harmes, and dangers, etc. and that they would confirme your, lawes, and redeeme your loſt liberties, veiw likewiſe his Majeſtyes reply to this petition, that he ſhould not count himſelfe ſafe until they had layd downe there armes, and delivered up his townes and magazines, which they detained from him, and that the tumults of London were ſuppreſſed, then veiw the replication of theſe now uſurpers to that replication dated the 29. of Iuly. That they deſired his then Majeſty to accept of this there juſt reply, that they could not diſcharge the truſt repoſed in them, for the ſafety of the King, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (marke that country men King and Kingdome) neither could they yeeld to theſe demands of his Majeſtyes, for (ſay they in that replication) they tooke up armes, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31168:13"/>the poſſeſſion of ſuch townes and maguzines, for the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of religion the ſafety of his Majeſtyes perſon, of the Kingdome and Parliament all which they ſaw to be in moſt eminent danger. (Marke againe al theſe reſolutions) and there in they likewiſe deſire that the King would returne to his court af whitehal, aſſuring him that his royal perſon ſhould be as ſafe there, as in any other place (they having aſſurance of the loyalty of the city of London to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and to that purpoſe they have taken care to prevent al danger which his Majeſty may juſtly apprehend. (Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen) by this petition, and the 2. replications with the order of Parliament made there on, Die Iovis Iul. 30. 1642. ordered by the Lords aſſembled in Parliament, that the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition and replication of the Lords and Commons be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and publiſhed, and that they be read by the parſons and curates in al churches of England and Wales. <hi>Iohn Browne Cl. Parl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could give you many more of there declarations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances, engagements, proteſtations, nay there oaths, and Covenants, where in they have ſolemnly ſworne to maintaine the King in his juſt priveledges, and to preſerve the perſon honour and dignity of the King with there lives and fortunes and that they would maintaine the juſt liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Freedomes of the people.</p>
            <p>But now let an inquiry be made, if theſe uſurpers you fight for, have done and performed the leaſt part of this replica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or any of theire remonſtrances &amp;c. &amp; firſt let is inquire what they have acted as to religion. Which they.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Have not only lacerated and tourne to peeces the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals thereof, but they have quite aboliſhed and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lely extirpated the very rootes and branches therof. Have they not in there very night marches (in which they were conducted by the wofull light of Burning townes) few ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king reſiſtance al being aſtoniſhed at the prodigy thereof
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31168:14"/>ſeeing the churches themſelves polluted with horſes and even committing beaſtly acts therein, virgins with rapes, and the cryes of the churchmen heard louder, and farther then the drummes, and trumpets of thoſe you maintaine, ſeeing the pollution of holy things thus trampled upon, nay holy and godly miniſters impriſoned and turned out from there ſtockes, and (that not al) but put to death for preaching the word of God according to there conſciences, and this being done have they not put in anabiptiſtical, ſchiſmatical fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, doe they not ſuffer your pulpits to be adulterated by coblers, tinkers, weavors &amp;c. Who teaceth nothing but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition conſpiracy, falſe doctrine and Hereſy from which good Lord in his due time deliver you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next let us make an inquiry concerning the Kings per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and dignity, which they have ſo often called God to witneſſe and other imprecations in there printed acts (but diſſembled deeds) that they deſired God to deale by them &amp; theres, as they dealt by his then Majeſty and progeny, which God grount.</p>
            <p>I ſay (Countrymen) let us inquire if they have not (in ſtead of maintaining him in his royal dignityes) impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned his ſacred perſon, and in ſtand of preſerving his royal life if they have not wilfully murthered him in a moſt ignominious way, as you already heard, and in ſtead of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Crownes to flouriſh upon him &amp; his poſterity, they have ſold them to Goldſmiths, and aboliſhed his poſterity for ever ſo farre as in them lyes, and this was there cheifeſt aimes of there firſt taking up armes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly enquire after your freedomes and liberties (deare Countrymen) behold whom you made as Gods a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, have they not ſacrifized your bloods to there fortunes, doe they not drive you on, upon al occaſions in the front of battles and ſtormes, as ſheepe to the ſlaughter. What navyes muſt be prepared, what armies raiſed, what
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31168:14"/>warres proſecuted, what cities deſtroyed, nations depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated on the only effects of there opinions, and none of al this againſt Heathens or antichriſtian enemies; but even againſt there owne fellow ſubjects, and neighbouring proteſtant bretheren, with whom there ever was firme league until ſuch ſycophants came to be rulers over you.</p>
            <p>Muſt they not be judges and Iuries of your bloods; fortunes, behaviours, and eſtimations? wil they not utter thinges according to the dictates of there owne affections? doe they not meaſure al things by the circle of there owne advantages? have they not made your publicke plentyes quitt the preheminence to there private profits? have they not made al that is yours ſerviceble to there amplitude; in a word, have they not ſacrifized your blood and fortunes to there arbitrary wils, and have they not effuſed blood in theſe warres at no rate and cheriſhed deviſions purpoſely to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe what they have obtrined hitherto, to be Kings and emperours, over you, in treaſuring up vaſt ſummis of monyes from you, reſolving to leape into an authority of a more hopeful permanency; and have not you brought this upon your ſelves by ſighting for and riſing with them upon al oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions; but goodneſſe for bid that ſuch earthtly wormes ſhould continue over you after ſuch a manner as they have done in making there progreſſes through ſmoaking cities, &amp; over the trampled bodies of halfe dead men, and continuing in the exhauſting al that is yours, rather then they ſhould be exhauſted.</p>
            <p>O countrymen looke but upon there waies a little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and take the length of this my proſpective glaſſe, and you ſhal perceive, that they know if the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the publicke ſhould be regulated according to the lawes of God, by the judgement of a pious and godly Prince, then they muſt become baſe, low, and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:31168:15"/>that they ſhould be expoſed to prey and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reption.</p>
            <p>They are neither like the heathens a as Hannibal who ſayd, <hi>Miles parce ferro?</hi> and Marcellus, wiſhing he could quench the flames of burning Syracuſa) no they deſire not to bye peace at ſo deare a rate, nor ſell there dominations ſo cheape, neither would they immitate Tytus (lyfting up his hands and eyes to heaven) wept over the Carkaſſes of the Iewes. No, they chuſe rather to ſtrutte it out with pride, and make themſelves inebriate with paſſion, and ſtrengthen there fury with deſolation, nought but in exorable wrathes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite with there diſloyal mindes. But let them beſure that our merciful Lord, wil be offended with the long continuance and theſe laſting malignityes of there undertakings, they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ceaſed to be what they profeſſed long ſince, they have forgone there declared innocence, and in ſtead of increaſing in reputation of godlineſſe and a good cauſe (which they then pretended to have in hand) they have built up there towers of fury and malice againſt al goodneſſe, both as concerning your religion and eſtates (nothing at al eſteeming of what our ſaviour ſayd) when he commanded al ſcandals to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooved from religion and out of the temple of the Lord dooming a Milſtone to be hanged about there neckes and caſt into the ſea, and nothing eſteeming of another rule of our ſaviours, love they neibour as they ſelfe.</p>
            <p>I muſt tel you countrymen the gentiles in times paſt were amazed at the charity of Chriſtians, to ſee how they loved each other but now the heathens, behold amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians brother againſt brother, father againſt Sonne, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying on another, and butchering each other, proſecuting, and perſecuting on another with endleſſe hatred, which can not be but a ſad Harmony in the greateſt of there Iubila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; now for al theſe things are dayly ſeene by you, yet you wil cleave to theſe monſters of mankind, you have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31168:15"/>rather chuſed to periſh with them, then to live a godly, quiet, and a ſober life, under your King the choſen on of God.</p>
            <p>O countrymen I be ſeech you by the mercies of God and in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, to forſake theſe rulers (who have forſaken God and you, theſe devourers of holineſſe, who have enough to beſtow on there owne edifices but nothing to beſtow on the repairing the Temples of God, but rather pulling downe the churches as they doe dayly amongſt you reedifiing there owne buildings, as it is in Agge the 1. and the 4. verſe. It is time for your ſelves to dwell in your houſes and this houſe to lye waſte.</p>
            <p>O ſuch wretched cormorants, who doe not onely let the houſes of God liewaſte, but utterly pul them downe, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe lands with the ſpoyles thereof, yet theſe ſacrilegious perſons are accounted by you good Chriſtians, yet you ſticke and adhere to them who make there buildings as it is ſpoken in the 6. chap. of Ioſhua and the 26. verſe. Not laying the foundations thereof in the blood of there bodyes, but in the ſpoyle of there ſoules, which God in the concluſion wil make them as ſwallowes neſts, which in the winter fall downe of themſelves: and wil you yet thinke upon ſuch people, wil you ſtil, deny your obedience to your King, who would there on doe as Noah did after the ſtood who built an alter to the Lord Gen. the 8. and the 20. verſe.</p>
            <p>I wil here conclude deare countrymen with this my laſt adviſe to thee. Which is. That thou forſake this pretended Parliament who have brought thee to this miſerable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that they have left no authority in England able to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle peace; your lives &amp; fortunes being liable to there luſtful wils by illegal accuſations blanke impeachments, threatning declarations who have put out the eyes of the Kingdome (the two univerſities of Oxford &amp; Cambridge) knowing that learning is a ſteppe to Religion, &amp; both to your lawes &amp; liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31168:16"/>and al enemies to there barbarons, irrational and illegal way of Government, al which when you tooke part firſt with theſe members, wee that have Chriſtianity doe beleive that you were ſeduced by theſe faire pretences of defending Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, King, lawes, and liberties, which they firſt held to you; and you thereby being unwilling to have a Parliament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by the ſword and conſequently your ſelves, and you not thinking that they could ſo farre prevaricate as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire againſt King, Parliament, and your ſelves, to the utter ſubverſion of al lawes, liberties, and the fundamental Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Land, betraying religion unto Heretickes, and Schiſmatikes, ſharing the ſpoyles of 3. Kingdomes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, &amp; now reſolving to enrich themſelves more in forraigne Lands, I ſay that (as my ſelfe was once at the firſt blinded) you my countreymen had no intention they ſhould be ſo farre intruſted as you have found to your greife they have engaged you before you were aware: (but thinke it not yet too late to draw backe your feet, and yet ſtippe the bridle out of your mouthes, with which bit they thinke they have you at there checke, having girt the ſaddle ſo faſt to your galled backes, and they as ranke riders mounted, who have not only ſpurred you out of your eſtates, lawes; and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, but wil ſpurre you into hel by new oathes, Treaſons, Covenants, &amp;c. If you take not the more heed, and be not the more reſolute, for now they have Squeezed what they can out of the Kings party, they cal them home, beginning to make up there bottomeleſſe veſſels ful out of your eſtates who have beene there freinds.</p>
            <p>Now I have ſhewed you the Lyon whome they hunted after (the Lord of the forreſt) not only to be ſicke and weake and ſo become a prey to them, he is not only goared by the oxe, bitten by madd doggs, and kicked by Aſſes, and as our ſaviour was ſpittedon by phariſes, but even as our ſaviour was become a prey and cruſified for our ſinnes, ſo was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31168:16"/>your King for your lawes liberties, and the ſinnes of the whole three Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>Now to al Chriſtian Princes I ſpeake to you eſpecially of blood or the ſame religion which this martired King Charles the, firſt was.</p>
            <p>Looke I ſay (you neibouring Kings and Princes) upon this ſad example, unheard of Preſident, and unparelled violence, and the Lord graunt you may apply it to your owne ſoules, and lay your councels and forces in conjunction to make examples of ſuch murtherous ſubjects, thereby you ſhal not only feare your owne people from the like attempt but reeſtabliſh him who no doubt may be able to helpe any of your greatneſſes in ſuch or any other diſtreſſe, and I am confident wil be willing to his utter moſt power. And you wil have (O Princes) the hearts and praiers of al our gracious Kings leidge people in his three Kingdomes of England Scotland and Ireland, for your redemption of them likewiſe from ſlavery and bondage, to which I cry. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:31168:17"/>
            <head>THE EPILOGUE.</head>
            <head type="sub">And declaration of the penman.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Gracious Souveraigne.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO ſhew your gracious Majeſty that I love my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſo much that I could devote my ſelfe to death for it as the Decij in Rome have done and that I reſolve to be ſuch, <hi>Quem neque pauperies, neque mors, neque vincula terrent;</hi> I (in the preſence of God and in the name of al the freeborne commoners of England) doe declare, that there is no legal Parliament in England nor lawful Government in Scotland and Ireland, that there is not 495. Commoners by names of Knights and Burgeſſes neither is there a houſe of Lords, nor is there a King with out any of which by the knowne lawes of England, petition of right by which Kings formerly knew what was theres, and the ſubjects theres, nor by there ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances remonſtrances and declarations made in the yeares 1642. 1643. where in they declared they intended not, neither could they make law without his them Majeſtyes conſent; I doe farther proteſt againſt thoſe arbitrary, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting, and uſurping few members remaining at Weſtminſter, that what ever they have done, or ſhal doe, as thay now are, is void, and null by law ab initio, and of none of effect by there owne doctrines, and judgements declared in there ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance made by them the 20. of Auguſt 1647. where in they made void ab initio al votes, ordinances, and orders, paſſed by the then Lords and Commons from the 26. of Iuly 1647. to the 6. of Auguſt following, when there ſpeaker with ſome other renegadoes of them huried away to the army then at Windſor, and this faith I reſolve to live and die in as</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſtyes loyal ſubject.</hi> Wendy Oxford.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:31168:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
